Guide to the John E. Parsons Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Edward Parsons papers
1960-1976
MS 792
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(7 boxes)
The papers consist of manuscript drafts, research notes, correspondence, and copies of original documents concerning the unpublished work The Aroostock Dispute and the Bounding of Maine. Also included is correspondence related to research and publication of West on the 49th; Red River to the Rockies, 1872-1876 (1963) and copies of other published writings of John E. Parsons.
Parsons, John Edward, 1903-1976
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. John E. Parsons to Beinecke Rare Book Library, 1976; transferred to Manuscripts and Archives, 1977
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers of John Edward Parsons (1903-1976), lawyer, naval officer, and historian, consist almost entirely of drafts anad corrected copies of an unpublished historical monograph, entitled "The Aroostook Dispute and The Bounding of Maine", and research materials used in its preparation. The manuscript narrates the diplomacy and survey of the Maine-Canada border in the 1840's and is a logical extention of the author's earlier work on the history of the demarcation of the Canadian-U.S. boundry west of the Great Lakes:West on the 49th parallel: Red River to the Rockies, 1872-1876(New York, 1963).
Two holographs by James Duncan Graham and Thomas J. Lee have been transferred from this collection to the Graham Papers in the Beinecke Library. Photographs of John E. Parsons, and life at Yale during the 1920's, have been transferred to the Yale Picture Collection, Individuals Series, under the surname Parsons.
Biographical / Historical
John Edward Parsons
Graduating from the Yale Law School in 1928, John had the interesting experience of a year's service as law clerk to Chief Justice William Howard Taft of the U.S. Supreme Court. He was associated with Winthrop, Stimson, Putnam & Roberts in New York from 1929 to 1936 and has since been independently engaged in practice, also devoting considerable time to writing. He is the author of The Peacemaker and Its Rivals (1950) and Henry Deringer's Pocket Pistol (1952), both published by William Morrow & Company, and of The First Winchester, which is still to be published, and is the coauthor of Firearms in the Custer Battle (Stackpole Company, Harrisbary, 1953). He has contributed articles and book reviews to the New York Historical Society Quarterly, the Atlantic Salmon Journal, and The American Rifleman.
He was admitted to the New York State Bar in 1931 and belongs to the Association of the Bar of the City of New York, of whose committee on state legislation he was a member from 1935 to 1940. He is a trustee of both the New York Historical Society and the Lenox (Mass.) Library Association and from 1939 to 1941 served on the board of directors and the executive committee of the Radio-Keith-Orheum Corporation.
John, who was on active Navy duty from May, 1942, to November, 1945 (lieutenant, then commander), served for forty months as assistant U-boat tracking officer at the Headquarters of the Commander-in-Chief of the U.S. Fleet in Washington, with temporary duty in London in 1943 and aboard the Guadalcanal in the Atlantic in 1944. He was awarded a Navy Commendation Ribbon, A Navy Unit Citation, and the Order of the British Empire. In December, 1953, he was transferred to the Retired Reserve.
On June 27,1927, he was married in Tuxedo Park, N. Y., to Fanny Haven Wickes. They had three chidren: Fanny Forsyth, born January 3, 1930, Richard Arnot on November 18, 1935, and John E., Jr., on January 11, 1938. Fanny, who graduated from Foxcroft in 1947 and then attended Bennington with the class of 1951, was married on January 20, 1951, to Edward D. Culleton and has two children: Dale Arnot, born July 18, 1952, and Ruth Mcllvaine on May 15, 1954. Hohn, Jr., was a member of the St. Paul's class of 1956.
Thirty Year Record of the Class of 1925, Yale College, pages 286-287
Aroostock War, 1939; Maine -- History -- 1775-1865; New England; Authors; Historians; Parsons, John Edward, 1903-1976
- Inventory
  - Manuscript of "The Arrostook Dispute and The Bounding of Maine":
    - Chaps. 1-12. Ribbon copy corrected to March, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Chaps. 13-19. Ribbon copy corrected to March, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Corrected copy. Pp. 1-123 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Corrected copy. Pp.124-249; with footnotes, bibliography (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - First draft, 1970-71. Chaps. 1-12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - First draft, 1970-71. Chaps. 13-19 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript of "The Aroostook Dispute and The Bounding of Maine":
    - First draft; revisions, 1970-71, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - First draft corrected, 1970-71, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - First draft corrected; revised introduction, 1970-71, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Revisions, August, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Revised drafts. Chaps. 1-14 (Box 2, Folder 11 - 12)
    - Revised drafts. Chaps.15-19. Corrections and recopies (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Original manuscript and outlines (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Drafts of new chapters. 1969 Jan - Feb, 1969 January - February (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Old 2nd xerox copy. Incomplete (Box 2, Folder 16 - 17)
    - Revised pages for xerox copy; and old pages (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Addenda and Rutgers University press and readers report (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Thomas Bartlett Papers. Miscellaneous xerox copies (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - James B.Bucknall Estcourt Papers:
    - Miscellaneous xerox copies (Box 3, Folder 21 - 22)
  - John Fairfield Papers:
    - Miscellaneous xerox copies (Box 3, Folder 23 - 26)
  - Sir John Harvey Papers:
    - Miscellaneous xerox and typescript copies (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous xeros copies (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Issac Hodsdon Papers. Miscellaneous xerox copies (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts relating to Maine. Xerox and typescript copies (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous printed sources relating to Maine: (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Land Agents reports. Xerox copies (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Articles, pamphlets, newspaper clippings. Xerox copies (Box 4, Folder 33 - 34)
  - "The Aroostook Dispute and The Bounding of Maine":
    - Early research notes, 1964-66, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Research notes, 1968-69, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Research notes on the St. John River, 1966-68, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Miscellaneous research notes, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Maps and topographical drawings. Photographic copies (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Illustrative material. Photographic copies (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Aerial photographs of Maine border (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence relating to research and publication, 1964-68, 1964-1968 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence relating to research and publication, 1968-76, 1968-1976 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence relating to research and publication of Parsons, West on the 49th Parallel ...(1963), 1960-72, 1960-1972 (Box 6, Folder 44 - 45)
  - Published and unpublished writings of John E. Parsons: author's manuscripts (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Published writings of John E. Parsons:
    - Author's copy of Catalogue of a Loan Exhibition of Percussion Colt Revolvers and Conversions ...(N.Y., 1942) (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Author's copy of Sam. Colt's Own record ...(Hartford, 1949) (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Author's copies of Firearms in the Custer Battle ... (Harrisburg, Pa., 1953); A student at New York University in 1847 ...(N. Y., 1954); "New Light on Old Colts" (1955); "A Grandfather in the Gold Rush..." (1957); "Steamboats in the 'Idaho' Gold Rush" (1960) (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Author's copies of "Nine Cousins in the California Gold Rush"(1964); "Down the St. John River"(1969); "St. John Headwaters Revisited"(1970); Review of Frederick Merk, Fruits of Propaganda in the Tyler Administration (1971) (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Newspaper clippings on environmental problems (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - "History of the Wild Lands of Maine". Mimeograph copy (Box 7, Folder 52)